William Temple Franklin Papers 1775-1819 Mss.B.F86
American Philosophical Society
- William Temple Franklin Papers, 1775-1790; Mss.B.F86; 4.5 lin. feet
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1784 December 14; ALS, 3p.; Bache, Richard
    His opinion of the wine sent by Baron De Feriet. Cannot expect much from Congress with regard to application made by Dr. Franklin in behalf of William Temple Franklin. Disposition of funds received from Robert Morris.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1784 December 16; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, William
    Sends a letter by Dr. [John] Jeffries's balloon from Dover; glad to hear of his son's safe arrival in Paris, etc.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1784 December 17; ALS, 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Will be glad to have a room at Passy for the winter.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1784 December 20; ALS, 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Inquires about a pension or college for two young boys.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1784 December 22; ALS, 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    At this instant there is an accommodation on foot between Mr. [Alexander John] Alexander and Mr.[Thomas] Walpole and the Commissioners of both sides have had one meeting and apparently have equal dispositions for peace. But at this instant Walpole is taking advantage of the security which Mr. Alexander supposes himself in, and is secretly endeavoring to take his person here. This is somethings worse than what the Devil himself would do. The object, therefore, is for Mr. Alexander to go to Ostend in the most private way possible, but they have good information that he is so watched that he would be taken on the way were he to go openly. Requests him, therefore, to fill up a passport for "John Brown allant à Ostende" which he thinks the Doctor [Franklin] will, without hesitation, sign. Gives minute instructions for the engagement of a place on the coach for Ostend for John Brown. Let it be said at the diligence that Mr. Brown is at St. Denis and will join it there.
    E. by A[lexander] J[ohn] A[lexander]. Request that the bearer may be kept until he is sent back with the ticket for the diligence and the passport, with advice as to the most convenient place to go to join the diligence.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1784 December 24; ALS, 1p.; Moore, Joseph
    Sends printing press ordered.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1784 December 27; ALS, 1p.; Alexander, Robert. Temple
    Announces his arrival in England. Willingness to execute commissions.
  - to William Temple Franklin, ca.1784.; ALS, 1p.; Alexander, William
    Begs his interest in his affairs with de Colonia, their "Rapporteur."
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1784.; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Alexander, William Jr.
    Requesting him to take charge of packets on his return journey to Paris.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1784.; ALS, 1p.; Bancroft, Edward
    Inquires if he can accept Mrs. [William] Hodgson's invitation to go to her country house.
  - to William Temple Franklin., ca.1784; ALS, 1p.; de Beauharnois, Chevalier
  - to William Temple Franklin., ca.1784; N. in 3d P. 1p.; de Beauharnois, Chevalier
  - to William Temple Franklin., ca.1784; ALS, 1p.; de Beauharnois, Marquis
    Declines an invitation.
  - to William Temple Franklin., ca.1784; L. 2p.; Mme. Caillot, "Blanchette"
    Tells of her long walk to their meeting-place and her distress at having to wait there and come back alone.
  - to William Temple Franklin., 1784; ALS, 1p.; Clarke, Anne
    Sorry to have missed his call; hopes to see him before he leaves England.
  - to William Temple Franklin., ca.1784; L.S. 1p.; Deschamps, -----
    With reference to balloons and gas for filling them, which he has for sale.
  - to William Temple Franklin., ca.1784; L. 3p.; Gien, Denis Germain
    Petition to obtain payment of his claim against J[ohn] S[c]haffer, an American, for food and clothing furnished to the latter.
  - to William Temple Franklin., 1784; L. 1p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    Sends Dr. Franklin's account; asks for a commemorative medal.
  - to William Temple Franklin., 1784; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Hesse, Mrs. Paddington
    Invitation to call at her house.
  - to William Temple Franklin., 1784; A.N.S. 1p.; de Mirabeau, Comte
    Informing him that Mrs. [Richard] Price has suffered a stroke of paralysis and her husband cannot receive them. Expects to go to Batl to see Lord Shelburne.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1784; A.L. 1p.; Morellet, abbé
    Tells of his journey and arrival in England. Went immediately to Bowood with Lord Fitzmaurice. Wishes to know when he proposes to return to France.
  - to William Temple Franklin, ca.1784.; L.S. L'Abbé du Rouzeau, Secretary. 1p.; The Lodge of Neuf Soeurs
    At a special meeting it was decided that the dedication of Dr. Franklin's bust should take place on the 18th, that the ceremony should not be too solemn, and that each member, whether present or absent, should be taxed 9 livres.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1784; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Riddell, Lady
    Inviting Governor [William] Franklin and William Temple Franklin to a card party.
  - to William Temple Franklin, ca.1784.; L.S. 1p.; Royer,-----
    Quoting prices of English books he has for sale.
  - to William Temple Franklin, ca.1784.; ALS, 1p.; De St. Aubin, -----
    Would like Mr. [Jonathan] Williams, [Jr.] to recommend him to some one who would sell his prints on commission in America.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1784; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Mr. and Mrs. William Sloper
    Inviting him to dinner to meet the Dean of St. Asaph and Mrs. Shipley.
  - to William Temple Franklin, ca.1784.; ALS, 1p.; Vaughan, Samuel Jr.
    Accepting invitation to dine with Dr. Franklin.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1784.; ALS, 1p.; Whitefoord, Caleb
    Thinks it will be well for him to go unattended to Mrs. [Mary] Hewson's.
  - to William Temple Franklin, ca.1784.; ALS, 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Asks for a passport for the types.
  - to William Temple Franklin, ca.1784.; ALS, 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Has invited Mr. Vernon, and Englishman of good family, his brother-in-law, Mr. Dawson, and Mr. Arthur to dine with William Temple Franklin; requests the latter to invite [John Paul] Jones.
  - to Williiam Temple Franklin, 1784.; ALS, 2p.; Wright, Patience. London
    Anxious inquiries about Dr. Franklin's health. Introduces a friend. Petition of New York Tories to King of England, and discontent of Tories in London, conducive to peace. Society for Constitutional Information; happy to find the honest Englishmen grown wise by experiences.
  - to Williiam Temple Franklin, 1785 January 24; ALS, 1p.; Alexander, William Jr.
    Encloses a draft on Paris.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 February 3; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Sicardy, -------
    Postponing the date for a concert.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 February 10; ALS, 2p.; Barclay, Thomas
    Inquires about wines in Mr. [John] Bondfield's account with the public, purchased for account of Dr. Franklin.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785] February 14; N. in 3d P. 1p.; The Ambassador of Sweden
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 February 16; ALS, 2p.; Grand, Henry
    Acknowledges receipt of buckles.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 February 18; ALS, 4p.; Jeffries, John, 1745-1819
    Acknowledging the courtesies and attentions he received during his stay in Paris.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 February 19; L. 2p.; Caffiéri, Jean Jacques
    Has just learned that M. [Jean Antoine] Houdon has been commissioned by Congress to make two statues. Is dissappointed at having been passed over, after having made Dr. Franklin's portrait and executed Gen. [Richard] Montgomery's tomb, without any charge or compensation whatever. Franklin and his son had both promised to recommend him to Congress. Still hopes they will interest themselves in his favor.
    (In French. In duplicate.)
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 February 24; ALS, 3p.; Bancroft, Edward
    Money affairs. Packet for Mr. Henry Grand. Sends parcel of books for Dr. Franklin. Writing machine for Mr. [Thomas] Jefferson.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 February 28; ALS, 1p.; Vernon, William H Jr.
    Asking for a loan of money.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 March 4; ALS, 1p.; Vaughan, Benjamin
    Requesting letters of introduction to the Governors of Martinique and Tobago for Mr. William Manning, [Jr.].
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 March 5; ALS, 1p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Inquires whether his letter with enclosures to Jonathan Williams, [Jr.,] Samuel Wharton and Samuel Lewis Wharton, at Phildelphia, have been received.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 March 5; ALS, 1p.; Loiselle, L
    Regarding the sale of his carriage.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 March 6; N. in 3d P. 2p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Has received several letters from America. Learns that Congress has reassembled at New York; delegates from Vermont have arrived with credentials; General Washington writes from Annapolis, of negotiations he is conducting for opening the Potomac to navigation.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 March 7; ALS, 1p.; Clarkson, Matthew.
    Introducing Mr. Randall. Offering services for commissions in New York.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 March 11; ALS, 1p.; de Geneve, Mellet
    Agrees to purchase his horse.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 March 11; L. 2p.; Caffiéri, Jean Jacques
    Wrote last month about the report that M. [Jean Antoine] Houdon had been commissioned by Congress to make two statues, in spite of the writer's former services and the promises made to him. Requests a definite reply on the subject.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 March 14; ALS, 2p.; Holker, Jean. Rouen
    Sends a case for Mr. [Thomas] Jefferson; also letters concerning the disagreeable affair of Samuel Wharton, with his house. Personal details.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 March 15; ALS, 1p.; Le Baron, -------
    Soliciting an appointment for his son, as Vice-Consul at Dieppe.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785] March 22; N. in 3d P. 2p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Asks if M. [Le Ray] de Chaumont [fils], who is going to America, will take as his servant, an Englishman who is recommended to him by the Duchesse de Lauzun.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 March 24; ALS, 2p.; Bancroft, Edward
    Acknowledges receipt of pamphlet. Rumors of negotiations for Commercial Treaty. His Parliamentary application in a good way to succeed. Introduces Dr. [Thomas] Ruston.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 March 31; L. 3p.; Caffiéri, Jean Jacques
    Has written to him twice without receiving any reply. Surprised at this, as he has always received a reply even when writing to Ministers, Princes and the highest Lords of the Court. Has, nevertheless, complied with his request, made through M. Lair de Lamotte, and delivered the plaster bust of Dr. Franklin to Delorme, to be packed and shipped by the latter. Encloses the bill for making the bust, packing, etc.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 April 4; ALS, 2p.; Grand, Henry
    Instructions how to send his coat, in order to escape Custom Home duties.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 April 4; ALS, 3p.; Barclay, Thomas
    Cause of delay in sending the case of china. Goes to Paris to settle the public accounts. Bill for tea and china for Dr. Franklin.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 April 8; ALS, 3p.; Caffiéri, Jean Jacques
    Declares his only object in executing a bust of Dr. Franklin was to transmit the portrait of a great man to posterity. Only received his actual expenses for the monument to Gen. [Richard] Montgomery. Claims he was entitled to more consideration for the above reasons, from Dr. Franklin and his grandson.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 April 11; ALS, 3p.; Elphinston, James
    His book and subscriptions for the same.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 April 12; ALS, 3p.; Vaughan, Benjamin
    Recalls his application for letters of introduction for his brother-in-law, W[illia]m Manning, Jr. Apologizes for letters of introduction given to Mr. Perry and Mr. Long. Dr. P[riestley]'s work on "Evidence of the Fathers respecting the Nature of Jesus Christ.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 April 13; ALS, 1p.; Grand, Henry
    Number of French officers in London. See Dr. [Edward] Bancroft.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 April 14; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Mesmer, Franz Anton, 1734-1815
    Making an appointment to explain the regulations of the Sociérté de l'Harmonie.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 April 14; ALS, 1p.; Loiselle, L
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 April 15; ALS, 2p.; Barclay, Thomas
    Encloses a letter to M. [Charles Alexandre] de Calonne; payment of fine by latter. Rumor that the freedom of l'Orient is to be transferred to Havre.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 April 25; ALS, 1p.; Gerardin, -----
    Invitation to meet a committee of the Société de l'Harmonie and pass upon Rules and Regulations.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 April 27; ALS, 1p.; Ridley, Matthew
    Introducing Benjamin Chew, of Philadelphia.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 May 2; ALS, 7p.; Jeffries, John, 1745-1819
    Requests to be recommended professinally to Mr. [John] Adams and family. Asks advice in the matter of Blanchard and aerial experiments. Blanchard's indebtedness to him and disposition to tax him to the utmost.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 May 3; ALS, 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Voyage to England and expenses of the same. Dr. [Richard] Price will give the list of books for Franklin Township. He advises against the use of solvents in Dr. Franklin's illness.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 May 9; ALS, 1p.; Coffyn fils,-----. Dunkerque
    Has received his letter for Chevalier MacEgan, Captain in the Berwick Regiment, but has been unable to discover his whereabouts; the Regiment is in garrison at Isle de Ré.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 May 16; ALS, 1p.; Dupré,-----
    Concerning the price of a press.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 May 17; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Gautier, -----
    Inquires about the price of his horse, and when it can be seen.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 May 18; ALS, 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Thinks Dr. Franklin could not do better than go to America in the June packet; hopes to join him at Havre.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 May 21; L. in 3d P. 1p.; de Wind, Baron
    Inquires about Dr. Franklin's health. Wishes to buy his cabriolet.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 May 22; ALS, 2p.; Leveux, James.
    With reference to a case of goods for Henry Grand, in England.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 May 25; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Vernet, Carle
    Makes an appointment to call on him. Hopes the painting he is going to make of his horse will be worthy of his acceptance.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 May 27; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Brongniart, Alexandre Théodore
    Recent books on French architecture.
    (Nn French.)
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 May 27; ALS, 1p.; Caslon, William
    Rumors of his intention to leave Paris. Sends specimen of type; hopes to receive recommendations to friends in America.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 May 29; ALS, 3p.; Grand, Henry
    Is exceedingly sorry to hear that he and Dr. Franklin are going to return to America. Mr. [John] Adams is about to go to St. James's for the first time.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 May 29; N. in 3d P. 3p.; Couture, Guillaume
    Reply to his inquiry about a work published on French architecture containing plans of houses and hotels of Paris. etc.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 June 6; ALS, 3p.; Dupé, -----
    Design for a seal.
  - to William Temple Franklin., 1785 June 6; ALS, 3p.; Jeffries, John, 1745-1819
    Request to secure the sanction of Baron de Breteuil, or Duc de Chartres to accompany M. [Jean François] Pilâtre de Rozier on a balloon trip from France to England.
  - to William Temple Franklin., 1785 June 6; ALS, 1p.; de Wind, Baron
    Accepts a commission to purchase harness. Asks for use of a jockey to try his horse. Invitation to dinner.
  - to William Temple Franklin., 1785 June 10; ALS, 1p.; Duke of Dorset
    Invitation to a musicale.
  - to William Temple Franklin., 1785 June 10; ALS, 2p.; Alexander, William Jr.
    Has searched unsuccessfully for the book on "Solvents for the Stone," requested by Dr. Franklin.
  - to William Temple Franklin., 1785 June 13; ALS, 2p.; de Wind, Baron
    Embarrassed for want of funds to discharge the debt due him.
  - to William Temple Franklin., 1785 June 18; ALS, 2p.; Deshayes, -----
    Offers to enter Franklin's service, if his son be also employed.
  - to William Temple Franklin., 1785 June 22; ALS, 2p.; Franks, David
    Begs for a loan of money to discharge his debts and leave Paris for America.
  - to William Temple Franklin., 1785 June 24; ALS, 3p.; Williamos, Charles
    Arranging for a suitable vessel for Dr. Franklin's voyage to America. Meréchal de Castries says if he can wait a little, such a King's ship shall be ordered as will give him every possible convenience.
  - to William Temple Franklin., 1785 June 29; ALS, 2p.; Limozin, Andrew. Havre-de-Grace
    Information of the arrival of Captain Nicholson's vessel in which Dr. Franklin wishes to take passage for America. Offers rooms at his house for Dr. Franklin.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 June 30; ALS, 4p.; Jeffries, John, 1745-1819
    Has been employed, professionally, by Mr. [John] Adams's family. Sends an account of his aerial experiments. Asks for suggestions and corrections.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 July 2; ALS, 2p.; Elphinston, James
    Sends good wishes for his voyage to America.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 July 2; L.S. 2p.; Garvey, Plowden. Rouen
    Arrangements for transferring the 129 pieces of baggage from the boat to the sailing vessel.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 July 6; ALS, 1p.; Royer, -----
    With reference to a proposal to exchange some books with William Temple Franklin or Dr. Franklin. Asks if there is no key for the printing press he bought from the latter.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 July 11; ALS, 1p.; Lotbinière, Michel-Alain Chartier de
    Apologizes for interrupting his preparations for the voyage; begs him not to forget the printing and prompt distribution in Canada, of the manuscript which he gave him; desires his and his grandfather's influence with Parliament on the subject of his seigniories on Lake Champlain. Encloses his manuscript concerning the formation of the Assembly in the Province of Quebec. [17p.]
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 July 12; ALS, 2p.; Chaumont, Le Ray de
    Letter from his son in America. Advice and good wishes for their voyage.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 July 16; ALS, 3p.; de Lamotte, Lair
    The disposition of the furniture left in Dr. Franklin's house. Encloses several accounts. Will always remember, with gratitude, the time spent with Dr. Franklin—his benefactor; always admired William Temple Franklin's attachment for his grandfather. Hopes to obtain, later, employment in America.
  - to William Temple Franklin, [1785] July 17; L. 1p.; ------, -----
    Thanking him for taking charge of his letters for America and wishing him a speedy and safe arrival.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 July 18; ALS, 3p.; Jeffries, John, 1745-1819
    Sends good wishes for his voyage. Offers his services for commissions, etc.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 July 18; ALS, 2p.; Bancroft, Edward
    Sends by M. [Jean Antoine] Houdon, who sets out this evening, a letter for his brother. Good wishes for thier voyage.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 July 19; ALS, 1p.; Le Vieux, -----. Rouen
    Encloses letters for friends in Philadelphia. Good wishes for their voyage.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 July 19; ALS, 2p.; Le Veillard fils, Louis
    Bids adieu to him on his departure and begs him not to forget him. Warns him against a too great ambition.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 July 19; ALS, 2p.; Limozin, Andrew. Havre-de-Grace
    Terms for freight, etc., from Masters of two different vessels.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 July 20; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Limozin, Andrew. Hawre-de-Grace
    Inquires at what time the porters shall call with the chaise.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 July 22; ALS, 1p.; Lemercier, -----
    Will place the sum of money to his credit as soon as he receives it from ----- -----.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 July 24 to 31; A.L. 4p.; Caillot, Blanchette
    Tells of her sorrow and distress on his departure. Narrates her visit to Paris and her dislike of the city. Received a letter from Mlle. B[rillion] describing Dr. Franklin's and his grandson's departure from Passy. Bids him adieu, as he is to sail next day, August 1st.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 July 27; ALS, 1p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume. Cowes
    Expresses his sorrow at seeing him leaving for America. Hopes to see him again but thinks his best prospects are in America.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 August 9; A.L. 8p.; Caillot, Blanchette
    Package which he gave to [Louis Guillaume] Le Veillard to deliver to her. Tells of Mlle. M----'s visit to her and the episode of the portrait given to the latter by him. Is treated well now and enjoys a little more freedom. Alludes to M. B[rillon]. Is looking forward to his return to France.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 August 10; A.L. 2p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Concerning various commissions which he promised to attend to for him. Sends last messages to some of his fellow passengers; urges his speedy return to France.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 August 15; ALS, 4p.; Fox, George
    Regrets his inability to show civilities to Le Ray de Chaumont [fils]. Gives news of various friends.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 August 30; A.L. 4p.; Caillot, Blanchette
    Does not know how to forward her letters to America; tells of departure of his cousins from St. Germain. Saw M. Brillon lately, who told of a proposed marriage for his daughter.Tells of her children and how she passes her time.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 September 13; A.L. 2p.; Caillot, Blanchette
    Tells of [Louis Guillaume] Le Veillard's visit to her and the details he gave of his and Dr. Franklin's departure from Havre. Has arranged with him how to forward her letters. Alludes to Mlle. Brillon's coming marriage.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 September 19; ALS, 1p.; Jay, John
    Pleasure on hearing of Dr. Franklin's arrival in Philadelphia and of his reception.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 September 23; ALS, 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809
    Welcoming him home. Anxious to hear about various friends.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 September 27; ALS, 8p.; de Lamotte, Lair
    The discovery of numerous debts contracted in Dr. Franklin's name by his steward, Finck; how the latter defrauded the trades people; the scandalous and false reports he is spreading about Dr. Franklin and his grandson. Particulars about the arrest of Cardinal de Rohan in the affair of the Queen's necklace; the Exposition of Paintings and Sculpture. Tells of his plans for the future. Learns that William Temple Franklin's baggage is still at Havre.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1785 Ocotber 9; ALS, 2p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Baggage remained at Havre. Is sorry for [Jean Antoine] Houdon, also, who had to leave behind him all his effects, tools, etc.; his works having their usual success at the Salon. Dined at St. Germain lately; alludes to William Temple Franklin's liaison with Mme. Caillot. Is sending him a few pairs of socks and wooden shoes. Has not been able yet to get the roebucks for him. Tells of the coming marriage of Mlle. Brillon de Jouy to M. de Malachelle.